Alberto is a former actuary turned data scientist. He has professional experience in data science, product management, and entrepreneurship. He is skilled at building new products and teams from idea to deployment and governance. His strengths are in management, strategy, product and customer validation, machine learning, the design of experiments, data visualization, and communication. While completing a computer science Ph.D. in dialogue systems and natural language processing, Alberto's setting up a new data science team at Tesla and authored the book *The Ethics of Al: Facts, Fictions and Forecasts*.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

### Tesla, Berlin (remote) — Sr. Revolutionary Actuary Data Scientist

APR 2021 - PRESENT

Building a new data science function and team for a confidential project.

## Futurely, San Francisco (remote) — Advisor, Product Management and Strategy

JUN 2020 - MAR 2021

Futurely helps high schoolers to make decisions about their future.

Alberto helped the founding team in the areas of customer discovery, product-market fit, willingness to pay, product strategy, early recruiting, machine learning MVP; and introduced the team to significant contacts for early PR.

### Miranda, Milan — Co-Founder, Advisor, Interim CTO, Data Science

SEP 2018 - JAN 2020

Miranda is a first Italian chatbot dedicated to automate insurance agents' front desk operations.

Alberto developed the proofs of concept, helped set out the product roadmap, technology specifications, and supported sales and customer onboarding. He co-founded the company and he's now an advisor of the board.

### Spixii, London — Founder, Product, Sales, Data Science

JAN 2016 - JUN 2018

Spixii is a boutique agency specialized in automation frameworks, chatbot solutions and customer experience optimization for enterprise insurance clients.

Alberto handled the company set up, product, and customer development. By designing experiments and interviewing hundreds of customers, he validated problem-solution fit with the creation of Spixii's first product - a chatbot for enterprise insurance services. Alberto built the Product Team and the Data Science Framework with in-house engineers and outsourced developers. He also helped to build the recruiting and sales processes and sold three enterprise contracts. In just over two years, Spixii built the best chatbot implementation in insurance for Zurich UK Insurance which received the British Claims Award 2018 for the best use of technology.

# **Deloitte, London** — Senior Consultant

MAY 2014 - DEC 2015

Alberto worked as a Senior Data Scientist at "HexScore", Deloitte Consulting Incubator's InsurTech flagship project. Alberto's selected technology requirements, built machine learning pipelines, supported sales pitches, managed pilots with clients, leading the development of the technical solution, and the product design. The core product was a big data platform that, combined with machine learning models, offered non-traditional motor insurance pricing and risk-assessing for insurance policies using telematics devices

### Various Insurance Companies (Chubb, Beazley, Munich Re), London — Actuary

JUL 2010 - APR 2014

Alberto's earlier career started in actuarial science. He holds a Diploma in Actuarial Techniques from the Faculty and Institute of Actuaries, developed statistical models for pricing, capital modeling, reserving, and data visualizations for management information reports.

#### **EDUCATION**

### **NYU Tandon School of Engineering, Abu Dhabi/New York** — *PhD*

2018 - EXP 2022

**Research interests:** Dialogue Systems, Natural Language Processing with low resources, Human-Computer Interaction, Responsible Al.

**Subjects:** Machine Learning (A-), Human-Computer Interaction (A), Design and Analysis of Algorithms I (A) and II (B), Big Data (A), Responsible Data Science (A).

#### **Publications:**

Chierici, Alberto, Nizar Habash, and Margarita Bicec. "The Margarita Dialogue Corpus: A Data Set for Time-Offset Interactions and Unstructured Dialogue Systems." In Proceedings of The 12th Language Resources and Evaluation Conference, pp. 476-484. 2020.

Chierici, Alberto, and Nizar Habash. "A View From The Crowd: Evaluation Challenges for Time-Offset Interaction Applications." In Proceedings of the Workshop on Human Evaluation of NLP Systems (HumEval), pp. 75-85. 2021.

Chierici, Alberto, Tyeece Hensley, Wahib Kamran, Kertu Koss, Armaan Agrawal, Erin Meekhof, Goffredo Puccetti, and Nizar Habash. "A Cloud-based User-Centered Time-Offset Interaction Application." Accepted for the 22nd Annual SIGdial Meeting on Discourse and Dialogue. 2021.

Chierici, Alberto. "The Ethics of A.I.: Facts, Fictions and Forecasts." Washington, DC: New Degree Press. Expected August 2021.

**Science Outreach:** Created the exhibition <u>Humans and Machines</u> for educating the public about Artificial Intelligence, and its social and ethical implications.

# Università degli Studi di Milano Bicocca, Milan — MSc Statistics

2008 - 2011

# Università degli Studi di Milano, Milan — BSc Physics

2004 - 2008

#### SKILLS

### Technical

End-to-end Machine Learning data-products, data visualization, responsible data science. Stack used throughout his roles(\*beginner - \*\*\*\*\*expert):

R***	HTML**	Spark ***
Python ****	Shiny ***	MySQL**
TensorFlow ***	Dash **	MongoDB*
Flask ***	Tableau ****	C++*
CSS **	H2O ****	Java*

#### Entrepreneurship, management, and design

Alberto spent his past six years in entrepreneurship, corporate innovation, data science, and product management. He led product teams using agile methodologies, acting as scrum master and supervising sprints. He managed virtual teams in different time zones as well as client projects nationally and abroad. Alberto mentors other entrepreneurs in the USA, Italy, UK, and UAE.

Alberto is obsessed with beauty and user experience. He always had an artistic spark and he self-thought the design methodology, graphic design principles, sketching. Alberto implements the lean methodology to validate people's problems, rapidly prototyping before crafting any technological implementation.

# **INTERESTS & OTHER ACTIVITIES**

Stock market investing - Implemented an automated strategy that performed 20%/year for the past 4 years. Passionate about hackathons, cooking, reviewing restaurants, cinema, reading, religions and philosophy, charity volunteering, classical music, functional training.

References available upon request.